Mss.Rec.7 Mss.Rec.7
American Philosophical Society
Stories in Chitimacha
1933, 1934
Mss.Rec.7
American Philosophical Society
2.0 Reel(s)
This collection primarily contains Chitimacha material, with some additional Nootka material, originally recorded on 23 wax cylinders by Morris Swadesh in 1933 and 1934. The recordings were transferred circa 1951 to 2 sound tape reels. Due to the poor condition of the original cylinders, the sound quality of the recordings is generally poor. Tape 1 contains elicited sentences, folklore, and autobiographical stories told in Chitimacha by Benjamin Paul, chief from 1903 to 1934, and Delphine Ducloux, the last known speaker of Chitimacha. Recorded in Louisiana in 1933 on 22 wax cylinders. Tape 2 contains elicited sentences, unidentified narrative, and some singing in Nootka by Alex Thomas. Recorded at Port Alberni, British Columbia, on 1 wax cylinder in 1934.
2 sound tape reels (1 hr., 53 min.): analog, 3 3/4 ips, 2 track, mono; 7 in.
Ducloux, Delphine
Paul, Benjamin
Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
Thomas, Alex
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Morris Swadesh in 1950.
Related Archival Material
Morris Swadesh's Chitimacha dictionary file, Chitimacha-English dictionary, fieldnotes, grammar, texts, vocabulary, and other material can be found in the Franz Boas Collection of Materials for American Linguistics (Mss.497.3.B63c.)
Animals--Folklore; Basket making; Chitimacha Indians--Folklore; Chitimacha language; Indians of North America--Migrations; Nootka Indians--Music; Nootka language; Sound recordings
- Audio recordings
  - Rabbit Splits His Nose, 1934; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:50; Paul, Benjamin; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Cylinder recording) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Animals--Folklore; Chitimacha Indians--Folklore; Chitimacha language; Louisiana; Rabbits--Folklore
  - Grandmother Teasing Song; How the Indian Came, 1934; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:45; Paul, Benjamin; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Chitimacha Indians--Folklore; Chitimacha language; Indians of North America--Migrations; Louisiana
  - The Chart of the Sky; Old Owl Woman, 1934-09-17; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:15; Paul, Benjamin; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Chitimacha Indians--Folklore; Chitimacha language; Louisiana; Owls--Folklore
  - Rabbit Splits His Nose; Wolf and Turtle, 1934; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:24; Paul, Benjamin; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Chitimacha Indians--Folklore; Chitimacha language; Louisiana; Rabbits--Folklore; Turtles; Wolves--Folklore
  - Mockingbird and Owl; Two Chickens; When the World Began [1 of 2], 1934; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:54; Paul, Benjamin; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Chickens; Chitimacha Indians--Folklore; Chitimacha language; Creation--Mythology; Louisiana; Mockingbirds--Folklore
  - When the World Began [2 of 2]; Some Sentences Continued and Concluded; The Neighbors' Fight [beginning], 1934; 06-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:38; Paul, Benjamin; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Chitimacha Indians--Folklore; Chitimacha language; Creation--Mythology; Louisiana
  - Chitimacha sentences, 1934; 07-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:25; Paul, Benjamin; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Chitimacha language; Louisiana
  - The Snake-Bite Story; Chitimacha Phrases, 1934; 08-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:27; Paul, Benjamin; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Chitimacha Indians--Folklore; Chitimacha language; Louisiana; Snakes
  - Stories in Chitimacha, Cylinder #9 (Deer and Turtle as Rivals [1 of 2]?), 1934; 09-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:41; Paul, Benjamin; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Scope and Contents note
    Untitled cylinder. May be "Deer and Turtle as Rivals (part 1 of 2)"
    Animals--Folklore; Chitimacha Indians--Folklore; Chitimacha language; Deer; Louisiana; Turtles
  - Deer and Turtle as Rivals [2 of 2], 1934; 10-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:52; Paul, Benjamin; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Animals--Folklore; Chitimacha language; Deer; Louisiana; Turtles
  - DuPlessis in League with the Devil [1 of 2], 1934; 11-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:09; Paul, Benjamin; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Chitimacha language; Devil--Folklore; Louisiana
  - DuPlessis in League with the Devil [2 of 2]; How Longhorn Got Her Name, 1934; 12-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:58; Paul, Benjamin; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Chitimacha Indians--Folklore; Chitimacha language; Devil--Folklore; Louisiana
  - Marriage of the Chief's Daughters, 1934; 13-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:47; Paul, Benjamin; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Chitimacha language; Louisiana; Marriage
  - The Snake-Bite Story, 1934; 14-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:41; Paul, Benjamin; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
  - Some Talk About Hunting, 1934; 15-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:07; Paul, Benjamin; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Chitimacha language; Hunting; Louisiana
  - Stories in Chitimacha, Cylinder #16, 1934; 16-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:59; Ducloux, Delphine; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Chitimacha Indians--Folklore; Chitimacha language; Louisiana
  - How I Learned to Weave Baskets, 1934; 17-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:03; Ducloux, Delphine; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Basket making; Chitimacha language; Louisiana
  - A Selfish Woman, 1934; 18-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:18; Ducloux, Delphine; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
  - A Selfish Woman, further 45-55, sentences 1-4, 1934; 19-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:12; Ducloux, Delphine; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Numbering in title refers to location of recorded material on original wax cylinder.
  - Chitimacha Speech & Songs, 1934; 20-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:07; Ducloux, Delphine; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
  - Chitimacha Sentences, 1934; 21-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:08; Ducloux, Delphine; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
  - Nootka Sentences and Story, 1933; 23-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:48; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967; Thomas, Alex
    Nootka Indians--Music; Nootka language; Port Alberni (B.C.)